ABHINAV ANAND

Associate Consultant Analytics | +91 9654385076 |

Email: abhinavanand221294@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhinav-anand221294/|GitHub: https://github.com/abhinav221294|

Kaggle: https://www.kaggle.com/abhinavanand22|

Certificate: https://olympus1.mygreatlearning.com/certificate/RRTWYQMN

SUMMARY:

I am looking forward to work on data, with a good Statistical knowledge and ability to identify the fine points of data and build insights. An Associate Consultant with having 4 + years of experience and 1 + Year of experience in Data Analytics Field worked on various tools and technology and data driven issue like Data Quality, Data Monitoring, Data Analysis, Gathering various insight from Data and Storytelling.

SKILLS

Machine Learning: Classification, Decision Tree, Random Forest, Regression, K-Means Clustering, Natural Language Processing.

Statistical Methods: Predictive Analysis, Hypothesis Testing, Descriptive Analysis, Principal Component

Analysis and Dimension Reduction

Programming Languages: Python, Java, HTML.

Scripting Language: Linux/Unix | Operating System Linux, Windows |

Database Language: SQL.

Database: Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, MS Access. **Data Extraction/ETL Tool**: Informatica PowerCenter

Data Reporting Tool: Tableau, Qlik Sense, Qlik Nprinting, Qlik Management Console, Power BI, Excel

Deployment Tool: Nolio6 | Ticketing Tool: Service Now. | Monitoring Tool: Control M Tools/Applications: PLSQL Developer, SQL Developer, Control M, Tecta Client, Putty.

EXPERIENCE

Associate Consultant Analytics • MetLife JUL 2022 - Till Now

- Working as Qlik Sense Developer.
- Creating Dashboards and Report for End Users.
- Analyzing the Data and building Insights.
- Gathering the requirement from various stakeholders.
- Creating Reports for MetLife Worldwide Benefits for Claims and
- Premium data.
- Testing deployment for Qlik Report in UAT and Production Environment
- Data Analysis and finding out the problems in the data and driven for a fix.
- Documentation of various SOP for report.

Tech Lead • Cognizant APR 2022 - JUL 2022

- Leading multiple applications
- Helping and managing multiple teams
- Identifying functional gaps and technical issue that need to be addressed before time.
- Coordinating with different stakeholders
- To ensure application performance/reports are as per KPIs defines.

Associate - Projects • Cognizant OCT 2020 - Apr 2022

- Worked on ETL tool like Informatica.
- Building Reports and analyze data using Qlik.
- Removing corrupted data and fixing coding and related problems
- Data analysis in Excel and Qlik to analyze the data pattern and fixing data quality.
- Deployment using Nprinting/QMC
- Maintenance of Qlik servers and Nprinting Severs

Programming Analyst/Trainee • Cognizant SEPT 2018 - SEPT 2020

- Worked on user incidents and fix in quick and effective ways well within agreed SLA.
- Report onboarding/Creation using Nprinting
- Sanity checkouts of functional behavior of applications in/after production deployment Monitor and Acknowledge batch/system alerts and take immediate action if any issue found.

PROJECTS

• Capstone Project: Movie Recommender System Using Hybrid Filtering and KNN:

A movie recommender system is basically a tool that helps streaming media platforms recommend users' favorite movies based on their interests and behavior. OTT platforms like Netflix, Amazon Prime Video, Rakuten Viki, Disney+Hotstar ,etc. will recommend movies based on our watchlist. It creates a list of favourite movies according to each individual profile. Using an AI-based algorithm that analyses the data, it goes through various possible options, and creates a customized list of items that are interesting and relevant to an individual. Web-based movie recommender systems like Movie Lens , Flick Metrix, Popcornlike will recommend movies based on our customized answers. Businesses just need to upload the data set and extract inputs from their users. After generating the recommendations out of inputs, businesses can apply preferred filters to adjust the final recommendations.

Tools and Technology used: Natural Language Processing, K-Nearest Neighbor, Exploratory Data Analysis, Statistical Testing, Python.

• Capstone Mini Project 1:

Explore the exploratory data analysis, giving insights from the Facebook dataset which identifies users that can be focused more to increase the business. These valuable insights should help Facebook to take intelligent decision to identify its useful users and provide correct recommendations to them using the 'likes' target variable.

Tools and Technology used: Simple Linear Regression, Exploratory Data Analysis, Statistical Testing, Python

• Capstone Mini Project 2:

Based on given data of visitors browsing for online shopping, build different clusters to know whether a person is only browsing and visiting multiple pages or also generating revenue for the shoppers as well. Analyze and compare the clusters formed with the existing Revenue Column.

Tools and Technology used: K means Clustering, Agglomerative clustering, SMOTE, PCA, Decision Tree, Random Forest, Exploratory Data Analysis, Statistical Testing, Python

Capstone Mini Project 3:

These datasets aim to analyze variables that are likely to influence the business across verticals like Banking and Restaurant Delivery using basic python concepts of for-loops and user-defined functions along with data manipulation and visualization techniques using Pandas and NumPy libraries. The goal is to prepare the learner to understand the basic ways to analyze business datasets and draw preliminary conclusions that would pave the way for more extensive Exploratory Data Analysis.

Tools and Technology used: Simple Linear Regression, Exploratory Data Analysis, Statistical Testing, Python.

AWARDS

- "ALWAYS STRIVING, NEVER SETTLING" award from Cognizant in 2022.
- "CREATING CONDITIONS FOR EVERYONE TO THRIVE" award from Cognizant in 2021.
- "ALWAYS STRIVING, NEVER SETTLING" award from Cognizant in 2021.
- "WORK AS ONE" award from Cognizant in 2021.
- Multiple Client appreciation

EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATE

- Great Lakes Executive Learning, PGP-DSE ONLINE in 2023 with Excellent grade.
- Galgotias University, Greater Noida U.P (B-tech Computer Science Engineering) graduated in 2018 with CGPA 7.84.